<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document> 

  <body>
    <section name="News" >
    <p>
      <strong>14 October 2015</strong> - Version 3.1.3 has been released.
      This version adds "Docked Frames" page manager that allows displaying Jas3 pages as tabs or independent frames.
      Several enhancements have been made to the application framework used for developing customized applications based on Jas3.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>22 August 2014</strong> - Version 3.1.0 has been released.
      The main goal of this release is to ensure compatibility with Java 8 and other recent versions 
      of Java Runtime Environment on all supported platforms. JDK 1.6 is no longer supported.
      See <a href="ReleaseNotes.html">release notes</a> for a list of other changes.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>6 August 2014</strong> - <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/freehep-users">Google group</a>
      has been created for Jas 3 related discussions, questions, and bug reports.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>22 May 2013</strong> - Version 3.0.0 has been released.
      Unlike earlier versions, 3.0.0 contains only the minimal set of built-in plugins. All extensions
      can be downloaded through the plugin manager. See <a href="ReleaseNotes.html">release notes</a> for more details.
    </p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Description" >
      
    <p>
      <strong>Jas3 is a flexible, extendable, experiment-independent interactive data analysis framework.</strong>
      Features provided by the Jas3 interactive shell and a suite of standard extensions include:
      <ul>
        <li>Plotting of 1d, 2d and 3d histograms, XY plots, scatterplots etc.</li>
        <li>High quality print output.</li>
        <li>Fitting (binned or unbinned) using an extensible set of optimizers including Minuit.</li>
        <li>Export of plots in a variety of formats including PS, EPS, PDF, SVG, GIF, PNG.</li>
        <li>Easy to learn GUI for performing common analysis tasks (plotting, ntuple-analysis, fitting etc.).</li>
        <li>More complex analysis can be performed using a variety of scripting languages (pnuts, jython, etc.), 
            or by writing Java analysis modules.</li> 
        <li>Able to read data in a variety of formats including: SQL databases, text-files (see also HEP specific features).</li>
        <li>AIDA compliant analysis system.</li>
        <li>Built-in editor and compiler.</li>
        <li>Simple spreadsheet capabilities.</li>
        <li>Logbook for recording analysis tasks, and optionally publishing results to the web.</li>
        <li>Highly modular structure allows addition, replacement or removal of modules 
            to customize application for a particular problem domain.</li>
      </ul>
      Many additional plugins can be downloaded through the Jas3 plugin manager.
      Examples include <a href="http://wired.freehep.org/">WIRED Event Display</a> and 
      <a href="https://confluence.slac.stanford.edu/display/ilc/lcsim+Getting+Started">org.lcsim analysis framework</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Jas3 was originally developed for use in High Energy Physics experiments,
      but it has found applications in a multitude of other fields.
      Jas3 in written in Java and makes extensive use of FreeHEP libraries. 
      Jas3 is developed and maintained by the FreeHEP team at 
      <a href="http://www.slac.stanford.edu/">SLAC</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      <a href="launcher.html">Launcher</a>
    </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
